Guide to the Joyce Matz Papers 1969-2017 MS 3050
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Public Relations, 1969-2009; 224600; 4 Linear feet
  - Biaggi, Mario, 1971-1975; 224197 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 12)
    Press releases and official statements for Mario Biaggi (1917-2015), a Democratic member of the United States House of Representatives from New York's 16th district (1969-1988). Biaggi was convicted of corruption in two separate trials in 1987 and 1988, and resigned from Congress in 1988. See also photographs of Biaggi with Joyce Matz in box 22, folder 8.
  - Catholic Interracial Council of New York, Inc., 1979-1980; 224427 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1)
    Press releases and clippings for this organization, sanctioned by the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York in 1934 to challenge racism and social injustice, which run contradictory to Church teachings. The Catholic Interracial Council honored actress Helen Hayes for her "lifelong fight against racial and religious bigotry" on 3 December 1979; see the autographed photo of Hayes posed with Joyce Matz, presumably taken at this event, in box 22, folder 8.
  - Coalition for Family Justice, Inc., 1992-1994; 224388 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 2)
    Notes, press releases, and clippings for the volunteer-run, nonprofit Coalition For Family Justice (now the National Coalition For Family Justice), founded in 1988 to "identify problems and advocate for systemic changes in the divorce and family court systems in order to make them fair, user friendly, accountable, and affordable," and to "provide victims and children involved in domestic violence situations with crisis intervention, information, support, legal access, and advocacy."
  - Correction Captains' Association, 1979-1987; 224354 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 3)
    Press releases and clippings for the Correction Captains' Association, Inc., which supervises New York City's prison system and correctional facilities.
  - Eastern Paralyzed Veterans Association [7 folders], 1984-1990; 224252 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 4-10)
    Notes, press releases, clippings, and publicity material for the Eastern Paralyzed Veterans Association, a chapter of the Paralyzed Veterans of America, an organization of veterans who have limited mobility due to service-related injury or disease.
  - Friends of the High School for Environmental Studies, 2002-2009; 224547 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 11)
    Joyce Matz served on the board of the Friends of the High School for Environmental Studies (444 West 56th Street), which opened in 1992 "in response to a growing consciousness of environmental issues and in anticipation of a rapidly expanding field of environmental professions." Includes meeting agendas, minutes, correspondence, and notes.
  - Gallery Passport Ltd., 1969–1981; 224366 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 12)
    Press releases and clippings for Gallery Passport Ltd., a New York City-based art tour service that booked trips to regional and foreign exhibits and museums.
  - Government and Community Together for Legal Lives, Inc., 1995-1998; 224364 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 13)
    Press releases, clippings, and fundraising materials for Government and Community Together for Legal Lives, Inc., an organization established in 1990 by Kings County District Attorney Charles J. Hynes to provide "school children with alternatives to drug use, delinquency and violence."
  - GreenFlea / Intermediate School 44 Flea Market, 1995; 224361 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 14)
    Press releases and clippings for GreenFlea, the antiques, crafts, and collectibles fleamarket held in the schoolyard of I.S. 44 at 100 West 77th Street since 1985.
  - International Festival of Flowers, 1983; 224206 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1)
    Press releases, clippings, and informational material for the International Festival of Flowers inside the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, 5-8 October 1983.
  - Julien, Alfred S., 1981-1983; 224193 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 2)
    Press releases and clippings for Alfred S. Julien (1910-1989), a New York trial attorney for whom Joyce Matz provided publicity.
  - Lloyd, Anamaria, 2000–2001; 224355 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 3)
    Notes, press releases, clippings, and publicity material regarding Anamaria Lloyd, who, in 1998, brought a successful class action lawsuit against Principal Life, then one of the largest life insurance companies in the United States. Principal Life, a mutual insurance holding company--and, thus, owned by its policyholders--sought to become a public stock company without compensating them.
  - Mount Holyoke Club of New York, 1982-1986; 224424 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 4)
    Press releases, clippings, and some correspondence regarding events at the Mount Holyoke Club of New York (250 West 57th Street). Matz was a 1947 graduate of Mount Holyoke College, in South Hadley, Massachusetts, the oldest of the "Seven Sisters" consortium of prestigious East Coast liberal arts colleges for women.
  - Nathan's Famous, 1973-1979; 227365 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 5)
    Press releases for Nathan's Famous, Inc., purveyors of hotdogs, which sponsored free, weekly, one-hour shows for children in its Times Square eatery and in its other regional locations, between 1973 and 1979.
  - New York State Office of Parks and Recreation, 1979-1981; 224993 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 6)
    Press releases and clippings for events and programs in the New York City regional venues of the New York State Office of Parks and Recreation.
  - People for the American Way, 1991-1992; 224359 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 7)
    Press releases and clippings for the "1992 Spirit of Liberty Award" presented to Hollywood entertainment lawyer Arthur B. Krim (1910-1994) by People for the American Way, a progressive advocacy group founded in 1981 to defend constitutional liberties, with emphasis on the First Amendment.
  - Pollack, William, 1979-1981; 224273 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 8)
    Press releases and clippings for Bill Pollack, a one-time professional baseball player who had become a successful attorney in Passaic, New Jersey. In 1979 he embarked on another career, as a nightclub singer. Includes correspondence regarding payment owed Matz.
  - Save the Whales Day, 1978-1979; 228021 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 9)
    Press releases (by publicity firms other than Joyce Matz's), clippings, and mayoral proclamations for the travels of FLO, a 110-foot inflatable humpback whale exhibited in cities around the United States to raise awareness of the perils of commercial whaling. In New York City FLO flew outside the United Nations.
  - Sills, Richard Reynolds, 2003; 224550 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 10)
    Press releases and publicity materials for computer scientist Richard Reynolds Sills and his method of detecting hidden weapons of mass destruction.
  - Student Athletes, Inc., 1995-1997; 224365 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 11)
    Notes and press releases for Student Athletes, Inc., an organization founded in 1989 to meet the growing need for educational and athletic programs to encourage New York City kids to stay off the streets.
  - Superior Officers Association of the New York City Housing Police Department [3 folders], 1980-1988; 224530 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 12-14)
    Press releases and clippings for the Superior Officers Association of the New York City Housing Police Department, which retained Joyce Matz to publicize "the spiraling crime rates within the 267 New York City housing projects caused by a lack of sufficient housing police manpower."
  - Upper Manhattan Mental Health Center, Inc., 1999; 224362 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 15)
    Second annual gala fundraising dinner of the Upper Manhattan Mental Health Center (now called Emma L. Bowen Community Service Center, 1727 Amsterdam Avenue), honoring John Babieracki, Executive Vice President of Morse Diesel International, Inc., 7 June 1999.
  - Velella, Guy J., 1980-1982; 224278 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 16)
    Press releases and clippings for Guy J. Velella (1944-2011), Republican, a member of the New York State Assembly from the 80th District in the Bronx (1973-1982), and a member of the New York State Senate from the 34th District, also in the Bronx (1986-2004).
  - Washington Square Outdoor Art Exhibit [3 folders], 1983-1984; 224210 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 17-19)
    Press releases and clippings for the 103rd (Spring 1983), 104th (Fall 1983), and 105th (Spring 1984) Washington Square Outdoor Art Exhibit.
  - Zeferetti, Leo C., 1978-1979; 224199 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 20)
    Press releases for Leo C. Zeferetti (1927-2018), a Democratic member of the United States House of Representatives from New York's 15th congressional district (1975-1983).
  - Zervas, John, 1979-1982; 224225 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 21)
    Press releases and clippings for the "Hot Dog King of Central Park." In 1977 Zervas won and quickly lost the exclusive right to sell hot dogs in Central Park after his arrest for fighting with other, unlicensed, vendors.
- Series III. General files, photographs, and audiovisual material, 1971-2017; 227677; 1 Linear feet
  Series III includes general files of newspaper clippings, tear sheets, and occasional notes that Joyce Matz conceivably meant to incorporate into the more specific categories of Series I and II; a folder of résumés and newspaper interviews; some photographs of Matz with celebrities and political figures (described below); and a small amount of audiovisual material (restricted due to the New-York Historical Society's lack of playback equipment).
  The general files are sorted chronologically, with undated material coming last. As with Series I and II, the sheer number of newspaper clippings saved by Matz in the general files prohibited the archivist from arranging material in strictly chronological order. The researcher should, therefore, consult every folder to catch items that may be out of place. The single files of biographical material and photographs follow the general files, and the audiovisual material is grouped in a container inside box 22.
  - General files [folders 1-2 of 8], 1978-2017, undated; 228286 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 22-23)
  - General files [folders 3-8 of 8], 1978-2017, undated; 228422 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-6)
  - Matz biographical, 1970s-2004; 224256 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 7)
    Includes various iterations of Joyce Matz's résumé, and two newspaper profiles of her: (1) Al Amateau, "The Woman Who Likes Buildings" from The Westsider (January 16-22, 1986), and (2) Edward-Isaac Dovere, "A Champion for Preservation" from Our Town (November 18, 2004).
  - Photographs, 1971-1985; 228127 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 8)
    Miscellaneous images, including several of Joyce Matz posed with actors Tony Randall and Helen Hayes (the latter presumably taken on 3 December 1979 when Hayes was honored by the Catholic Interracial Council of New York; see box 20, folder 1); Congressman Mario Biaggi (in 1971 and later; see press materials in box 19, folder 12); writer Brendan Gill; and Matz with her dog (Attila?) in 1977. Many of the prints were made by photographer Bill Mitchell.
  - Audiovisual [7 items], 1984-1997; 228037 (Offsite-box 22, Folder [container inside box 22])
    Missing Title
    U-matic videocassette labelled "Joyce Matz | Midday Show | WNEW-TV | TUES-6-5-84" (1984 June 5).
    VHS cassette labelled "Joyce on Midday 1984 WNEW-TV" (1984 [June 5]).
    VHS cassette labelled "Joy[ce] [Matz] | 4-21-## | 5-28-94 | May 1st" (1994).
    VHS cassette labelled "4/1/96 | Community Bd | Joyce Matz & others" (1996 April 1).
    VHS cassette labelled "WNBC TV | Joyce & Sam | 'How it Costs to Keep Your Pet Alive!' | Thursday evening | 11 PM" (undated).
    8mm film reel labelled "NYC" (undated).
    Audiocassette labelled "'Tony Randall' | Bloomberg News | WBBR-AM New York | November 1, 1997 7:00-8:00 AM | 1:53" (1997 November 1).
    Access Restrictions
    The New-York Historical Society lacks audiovisual playback equipment, so these seven items are currently unusable.